<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Republic of Christianity</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Generated by</resp>
          <name>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Katherine O'Bryan</name>
        </respStmt>   
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana
          University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013">2013</date>  
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title>The Republic of Christianity</title>
            <author>Dicey</author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
              <date when="1857-12">December 1857</date>
              <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
              <!-- <biblScope type="pp">16-19</biblScope> -->
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="article">
        <p>It is scarcely possible to read the greatest of Plato’s dialogues
          without instituting some comparison between his doctrines and
          those of Christianity. That the feeling of the reader toward the
          Greek Philosopher is different from that with which he views the
          sacred writers, makes the comparison none the less natural. It
          is provoked as much by points of marked difference as by
          others of strong similarity. First among the points of likeness is the;
          appreciation of the moral goodness of God. The divinity of Plato
          is not merely a God of purity, he is also a God of goodness and
          truth. It is (in Plato’s opinion) impiety to refer any evils to God
          as their author; God is good and goodness can be the cause of
          nothing but good. The wicked, if chastised, must be punished
          for their good, ‘God is the cause not of all things but only of
          blessings', (Rep. 380, 381.) It is blasphemy also to ascribe
          untruth in word or deed to God. He is not a man that he should
          lie. [(Rep. 382, 383/ The false views circulated by poets of'the
          divine nature were a principal cause of their banishment from Plato’s
          commonwealth, This belief in the moral goodness of the divine
          character is the more remarkable when it is remembered that
          Aristotle denied that the Gods could possess moral virtue.
          On the subject of the treatment of our enemies, the doctrines of
          Plato approach very near to those of Christianity. If Plato did not
          teach that men should forgive their enemies he asserted that the
          good man would injure no one, for that the bad were only made
          worse by injury, and that a good man could not be the cause of
          others becoming worse, (Rep. 335.)
          A striking verbal resemblance between the language of Plato and
          of the New Testament is seen in the description of the unity of the
          ideal state—that “ city which is at unity with itself/’ “ That state
          is best governed,” says Plato, “in which as in the body, all
          suffers when one part suffers,” (462.) It is impossible not to be
          reminded of that society where, “if one member suffer all the
          members suffer, or whether one member be honored all the members
          rejoice with it.” This passage is connected with another point,
          where the likeness between Platonism and Christianity is something 
          more than verbal. In the ideal state of Plato private property
          ceases. In his words, the best of states is that in which all men
          call the*same thing ° mine and not mine." (Hep. 463 ) The early
          history of the church also tells of a time when u neither said any
          one that aught of the things that he possessed were his own, but
          they had all things in common.” The resemblance of expression is
          striking; but there is more than a resmblance of expression.
          There is a view of Christianity which all established societies hate
          to contemplate, but which reappears at many crises of the world’s
          history. Anabaptists, Puritans, English Levellers, and many sects of
          modern times have felt that Christianity proclaims an equality, not
          in religion only but also in outward society. With tins view of
          Christianity, Plato’s communism has much in common. Connected
          with this part of Platonism, is the view of the position of woman, a
          subject on which Platonism and Christianity have points of resem-
          blance as well as points of the strongest contrast. Plato declares the
          equality, (except in strength) of the sexes : be therefore ordains an
          education for women, similar to the training prepared for his men.
          Christianity, though in a different spirit, proclaims the essential
          equality of man and woman. It tells that, in one point of view, and
          that the highest there is “ neither male nor female for we are all
          one in Christ Jesus.’*</p>
        <p>As the Republic draws to a close, another likeness to Christianity
          appears. Under a form hard entirely to comprehend, is sketched the
          vision of a judgment to come. Platonism like Christianity looked
          for a day when all men should appear before the judgment seat of
          God to answer for the deeds done in the body.
          The Republic has been compared to a church. The comparison
          is partly fanciful ; yet the resemblance between the two is consider-
          able. Both are at once societies on earth, yet with aims higher than
          those of any mere earthly society. Both are ruled by principles
          different from those ruling other states. Both protest against the
          errors of all existing communities. Both believe (though in a
          different manner and degree) in a God of goodness. Both seem
          incomplete without a reference to a future judgement.
          Yet striking as are the resemblances between Platonism and
          Christianity, the differences are greater. Platonism is not a system
          for the whole world. It is essentially Greek. For a time the
          reader fancies that the Republic is a purely ideal state, suitable
          alike for every land, till he is startled by some assertion, showing
          how entirely national Plato’s conceptions are. That Plato’s
          Republic must be a Greek town is explicitly stated. A marked
          distinction is drawn between the treatment in war, of Greeks and
          Barbarians. The Republic might not inaptly be termed an idealized
          Sparta; the tutelary Gods of Greece are to be worshipped in it,
          and on many subjects Apollo is to be appealed to through his
          oracle. More, however, than any one assertion, the vein of Greek
          feeling running through the dialogue, marks the ideal city as a Greek
          state. Connected with this feeling are the sensuous enjoyments,
          utterly at variance with Christian sentiment which are offered
          to the citizens. Thus the brave in battle are to be rewarded
          with crowns, and garlands, with the permission to embrace
          wThom they wil1, with seats of honour, goblets of wine, and long
          chines of beef. If they fall they are to be worshipped as
          Demigods. (Rep. 409.)</p>
        <p>But a more radical difference between the two systems appears in
          the fact that in Platonism all depends on the intellect: it is a gospel
          for those only of high mental powers. For the “ perfect character,1’*
          many moral qualities are required, but it is, above all,
          necessary that it have a readiness in learning (evftaOr'is) without this
          qualification any great progress in Platonism is impossible. Thht
          God is good is a conviction lield in common by Platonism and
          Christianity, yet it is perhaps when we consider the Platonic view of
          the Divinity that the difference between the two systems most
          clearly appears. The Gods of Greece are not deposed by Plato.
          He declares that legends injurious to their moral character are
          untrue, and that they must be forbidden by law. He plainly intends
          to retain the old forms of worship in his state. It is, nevertheless, not
          in his language about the Gods, that it is necessary to look for Plato’s
          idea of * Divinity.* Far above all his other theories, is the mysterious
          thought of “ the Good. *’ (rp ayador) What it is Socrates
          confesses he cannot describe. He can only express it under a figure,
          what the sun is in the world of sense that the Good is in the
          world of ideas. It is not truth or knowledge; it is above them,
          it causes them. The reader might suppose it to be a first cause, were
          it not that Plato speaks of it with a kind of religious enthusiasm.
          The whole of his philosophic training is intended to guide the soul to a
          contemplation of the Good; by a life long study the soul attains
          to a view of it. The Good has been described as God without
          the idea of personality. Such a notion of God which makes knowledge
          of the Divinity attainable by the intellect only, renders it
          impossible that the Divine nature should ever be known to any but
          the most highly gifted in mental power. The poor and the illiterate
          might in Plato's State enjoy many blessings, under the rule of
          perfectly educated philosophers; the knowledge of God was never
          offered them.</p>
        <p>In another respect Christianity and Platonism are strangely
          contrasted. Each was fundamently opposed to the state of society
          around it. But this opposition was different:	Plato to
          reform society, proposed in theory, a total revolution. Every
          institution of society needed reconstruction. To form his state—^-even
          when the philosopher should be King—it was necessary to begin
          •everything from the beginning : a complete system of new institu-
          tions was to be introduced. Christianity also was opposed to the
          society, in which it arose, yet it needed to produce its effects, no
          sudden revolution. Few of the institutions of the age, except
          idolatry, are specially denounced in the New Testament. It is not
          new forms of government so much as a new spirit, and a new belief
          that are required. The Republic of Plato remained a mere theoiy.
          Christianity revolutionized the world. Yet while acknowledging
          the great and essential difference between Platonism and Christianity,
          the mind is still impressed with their strong points of resem-
          blance. Though it be true that Plato's ‘‘Fair City” remains a
          mere Utopia, whilst Christianity is an existing fact; still in one
          point of view each are theories but partially carried out. If Plato's
          Republic still waits for its realization, till that yet distant day when
          tl Kings shall be philosophers or Philosophers be kings” Christianity
          itself, as a society, is but half realized. It too needs for its fulfilment
          that the Kingdoms of this world should become the Kingdoms of
          our Lord and of his Christ.”</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>