<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Nonagenarian </title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Generated by</resp>
                    <name>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Tiffany Saulter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date when="2013">2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>The Nonagenarian. I.</title>
                        <author>unknown</author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
                            <date when="1858-01">January 1858</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pp">55-61</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <tagsDecl>	
          <!-- Basic text formatting: bold, italic, underline, "normal," etc. -->
          <rendition xml:id="b" n="tiebp:bold" scheme="css">
            font-weight:bold;
          </rendition> 
          
          <rendition xml:id="i" n="tiebp:italic" scheme="css">
            font-style:italic;
          </rendition> 
          
          <rendition xml:id="u" n="tiebp:underline" scheme="css">
            text-decoration:underline;
          </rendition> 
          
          <rendition xml:id="n" n="teibp:normal" scheme="css">
            font-weight:normal;
            text-decoration:none;
            font-style:normal;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="mono" n="teibp:mono" scheme="css">
            font-family:Monaco,Courier,monospace;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="super" n="tiebp:super" scheme="css">
            vertical-align:super;
            font-size:80%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="sub" n="tiebp:sub" scheme="css">
            vertical-align:sub;
            font-size:80%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="lowercase" n="tiebp:lowercase" scheme="css">
            text-transform:lowercase;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="uppercase" n="tiebp:uppercase" scheme="css">
            text-transform:uppercase;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="capitalize" n="tiebp:capitalize" scheme="css">
            text-transform:capitalize;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="small-caps" n="tiebp:small-caps" scheme="css">
            font-variant:small-caps;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Blocks. -->
          <rendition xml:id="block" n="tiebp:block" scheme="css">
            display:block;
          </rendition> 
          <rendition xml:id="block-margins" n="teibp:block-margins" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            margin-top:1em;
            margin-bottom:1em;
          </rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="blockquote" n="tiebp:blockquote" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            font-size:90%;
            margin-left:3em;
            padding-left:1em;
            border-left: 1px solid gray;
            margin-top:.75em;
            margin-bottom:.75em;
            padding-top:.75em;
            padding-bottom:.75em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition corresp="#blockquote" n="tiebp:blockquote" scheme="css" scope="before">
            <!-- This turns off the default generated quotes for block quotes. -->
            content:"" !important;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition corresp="#blockquote" n="tiebp:blockquote" scheme="css" scope="after">
            <!-- This turns off the default generated quotes for block quotes. -->
            content:"" !important;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="codeblock" n="teibp:codeblock" scheme="css">
            display: block;
            font-size: 80%;
            margin-left: 1em;
            padding-left: 1em;
            border-left: 1px solid gray;
            margin-top: .75em;
            margin-bottom: .75em;
            padding-top: .75em;
            padding-bottom: .75em;
            font-family:Monaco,Courier,monospace;
            white-space:pre;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Inline -->
          
          <rendition xml:id="inline" n="teibp:inline" scheme="css">
            display:inline;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Alignment. -->
          <rendition xml:id="center" n="tiebp:center" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            text-align:center;
            margin-left:auto;
            margin-right:auto;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="left" n="teibp:left" scheme="css">
            text-align:left;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="right" n="teibp:right" scheme="css">
            text-align:right;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="justify" n="teibp:justify" scheme="css">
            text-align:justify;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="center-block" n="tiebp:center-block" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            margin-left:auto;
            margin-right:auto;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Indentation -->
          <rendition xml:id="hang" n="teibp:hang" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:2.5em;
            text-indent:-2.5em;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Indentation for verse lines. Results in a “hanging” indent if
					the line wraps. -->
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-01" n="tiebp:l-indent-01" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:4em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-02" n="tiebp:l-indent-02" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:6em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-03" n="tiebp:l-indent-03" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:8em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-04" n="tiebp:l-indent-04" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:10em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-05" n="tiebp:l-indent-05" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:12em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-06" n="tiebp:l-indent-06" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:14em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-07" n="tiebp:l-indent-07" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:16em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-08" n="tiebp:l-indent-08" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:18em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="indent" n="tiebp:indent" scheme="css" scope="before">
            /* text-indent:4em; */
            /* The above method of describing an indentation for, say, a paragraph is preferred.
            The method being used is in response to a bug in some browsers whereby a block
            element, like a paragraph, is erroneously re-indented after interruption by another 
            block element (like a list, which is valid inside a paragraph). */
            content:"\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0";
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- font sizes -->
          
          <rendition xml:id="small" n="tiebp:small" scheme="css">
            font-size:90%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="x-small" n="tiebp:x-small" scheme="css">
            font-size:85%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="xx-small" n="tiebp:xx-small" scheme="css">
            font-size:80%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="large" n="tiebp:large" scheme="css">
            font-size:110%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="x-large" n="tiebp:x-large" scheme="css">
            font-size:115%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="xxx-large" n="tiebp:xxx-large" scheme="css">
            font-size:120%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="bracket" n="teibp:bracket" scheme="css"/>
          
          <rendition corresp="#bracket" n="tiebp:bracket" scheme="css" scope="before">
            content:"&lt;";
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition corresp="#bracket" n="tiebp:bracket" scheme="css" scope="after">
            content:">";
          </rendition>
        </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head>The Nonagenarian</head>
                <head>I.</head>
                <epigraph>
                  <cit rendition="#block">
                    <quote>
                    <lg>
                        <l rend="indent(9)">Throughout all the isle</l>
                        <l rend="indent(6)">There was no covert, nor retired cave</l>
                    </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <bibl><author>KEATS</author></bibl>
                  </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <p rend="indent(1)">I was vastly delighted the other day by a visit from ir. y Oiu
                    friend, Major Cato, whom I had not seen for these many years.
                    He was noways altered either in pere^n or disposition, except
                    there might be a trifle more censoriousness in the one, and a <emph rend="i">leetle</emph>
                    more frailty in the other, yet notwithstanding, he is as hale and
                    hearty as he was twenty years ago. He has not had much wear
                    and tear since 1815, when he was severely wounded at Waterloo,
                    since which he has resided in a remote spot in Leicestershire, with,
                    no companion save a favourite dog, and with no pursuit save
                    warring against the lord of the manor concerning a certain right
                    of common. He is a confirmed celibate, though he said bis
                    resolution so to remain quite trembled at the sight of my sweet
                    grandchild, Rose, who only shook her sunny ringlets in reply,—
                    the auburn of twenty smiling at the snowy whiteness of eighty.</p>
                <p rend="indent(1)">Cato was deeply perturbed in spirit: one of the great objects of
                    his life was on the point of being defeated. He was a resolute
                    and incorrigible lover of the old world, everything which smacked
                    in the least of novelty, whether politically or socially, was an utter
                    abomination in his eyes. The Reform Bill was in his view the
                    greatest atrocity ever perpetrated, and to that he ascribed every
                    evil that has since befallen the land, from cholera downwards and
                    upwards. The object, however, which inspired him with chief
                    apprehension and abhorrence was the railway; this he never
                    ceased to denounce with the liveliest indignation, an indignation
                    which on the present occasion was changed into absolute frenzy,
                    by the kuowledge that it was then in contemplation to carry a line
                    of rails close at the foot of his garden fence. Hitherto he had
                    congratulated himself on being at least fifty miles from the track
                    of any of the snorting, thundering monsters, which were, as he
                    thought, ruining the country. To find his little Eden, though
                    destitute of an Eve, thus desecrated by the pollution of iron and
                    steam threw him into utter desperation, and he had set off to me
                    to see whether there were a spot in my own Berkshire 4 unknown
                    to fortune and to fame.'</p>
                <p rend="indent(1)">The ‘fast public of this sixth decade of the eighteenth century
                    would grow weary were I here to set down the abuse which my
                    old friend heaped on the age. Thomas Carlyle himself does not
                    take so gloomy a view of these latter days. Now, for my own
                    part, I confess that though nigh ninety summers have passed over
                    my head, not to say ninety winters, yet I still retain my affection
                    for the age—for the present age, whether that present be 1790 or
                    1832, or 1858. Whatever may be the apparent mass of evil, and
                    however ruinously that mass may seem to increase, there is always
                    co-existent with it a huge amount of good, though it may be not
                    so trumpet-tongued as its rival. This is a proposition from which
                    I derive the greatest consolation. I am now growing incredulous
                    to the cry which I have heard three distinct times, that the country
                    if not the world is hastening to destruction. The cry has often
                    been got up to serve the purpose of a party in the state. It has
                    often been raised by the weak and timid, wdio in every movement
                    ontvard saw a further advance to the world’s Tophet. It has
                    often been shouted shrilly forth by some sciolist philosophers.
                    'Man never is but alw ays to be blest;' a rule quite as true in the
                    case of kingdoms and cities as in individuals.</p>
                <p rend="indent(1)">Still there is no era of human history but what is pregnant witA
                    mischief at once to itself and futurity, only the mischief will not befal
                    us or our posterity from great wars, or from the great political
                    revolutions which from time to time convulse the earth. Nay, it
                    is in social positions that I look to find the germ both of good
                    and evil, present and future. I was sipping, my tea last night, and
                    meditating as I often do on the times, occasionally glancing at my
                    darling little housekeeper, who sate at the other side of the fire,
                    deep in the mysteries of some device of w ool work. Her presence,
                    poor child ! seemed to make me more cheerful than I had been
                    since the departure—only temporary, I fear—of old Cato, whose
                    gloomy railings at humanity in general, and of nineteenth-century
                    humanity in particular, had almost made me misanthropic, so
                    infectious is the malady of complaining. I had yielded too readily
                    to bis charges against the time, and in obedience to tbe universal
                    rule of action and reaction I was now beginning to be as strong
                    in favour as I had formerly been in opposition. The chief charac-
                    teristic of this age, I reflected, is its burning excitement, its
                    feverish haste, and its noisy uproar, all good so far as they are
                    unmistakeable signs of a far stretching vitality. There is no
                    corner of the land from John O’ Groats to Land's End which this
                    tremendous surging of the waves of sociality has not reached, and
                    not only reached but drenched. Every small towu has its
                    Athenaeum, and its Mechanics’ Institute; there are infinite asso-
                    ciations to be found in every county, for infinite variety of pur-
                    pose : some for Christianity, and some for virtual infidelity. The
                    last victory of this terrible force, whatever it may be, has been
                    over the tranquillity, or supineness, as my friend Hierechthrus
                    calls it, of the ecclesiastical portion of the state, and now the
                    poorer classes, the working men know not what to make of
                    the stupefying cry of popular preaching. Well, well, I caunot
                    tell how it all tends. Its ultimate issue is too much for my poor
                    old brain. Yet there are one or two results which cannot but flow
                    from all this noise and fever, and results too which are even now
                    come about, the effects coeval with the cause.</p>
                <p rend="indent(1)">Much clamour is never consistent with depth. The brawling
                    little brook as it rushes in foaming haste over the stones through
                    my neat garden makes far more noise now than it will when united
                    with the Isis two miles from this. Hence I am noway surprised
                    to hear that learning is shallower nowadays than it was when I
                    was young, and it was far different even then from what it seems
                    to be now. I wonder where we should now find a scholar such as
                    Erasmus. Even Oxford, whose spires were just now before me,
                    even that venerated abode of wisdom is now become an advocate
                    of shallowness. What means this Middle Class Examination ?
                    Lo it is all for the encouragement and the fostering of tinsel learn-
                    ing. Astonished, I ween, would those learned fathers be who
                    once wandered along the cloisters of Oxford, could they but look
                    down and behold the attenuated proportions whieh learning now
                    has got. But I must beware lest I fall into querulousness. The
                    longer I live the more am I convinced that silence and solitude
                    are essential to true excellence, or at all events to the attainment
                    of that excellence. I remember a saying which occurs, I think in
                    Gibbon's Autobiography, on this point—“ Conversation enriches
                    the understanding, but solitude is the school of genius.'</p>
                <p rend="indent(1)">This solitude is peculiarly difficult to procure in these times, as
                    it seems to me. Society has of late made large encroachments on
                    individuality. A man is now supposed by no means to exist for
                    himself, but merely as a tooth in the cogged wheel of the world.
                    Monasticism is swept away, and rightly, but there is a species of
                    private and unpretending retirement which ought to be preserved,
                    and the loss of which is highly detrimental to worth. Let a man
                    ever rush into the maelstrom of society, and woe to his hopes and
                    chances of exaltation. The fact is that to ensure truthfulness and
                    real sincerity in humanity, privacy is necessary, absolutely indis-
                    pensable. People of this age ridicule such privacy. Its upholder
                    is denounced as uncouth, reserved and selfish; though in real
                    truth his selfishness is no more than is right and defensible, a
                    selfishness which refuses to allow us to lose ourselves—and what
                    a fearful degradation that loss implies—so as to give trumpery
                    delight and support to a social system whose elements are rotten-
                    ness. I know a young man who had obtained a considerable
                    amount of distinction at yonder neighbouring university, and who
                    possessed not only large knowledge, but what is of far more con-
                    sequence a thinking and reflecting mind, to which learning
                    appeared only as worth a distinct equivalent, and no way priceless
                    or invaluable. He ridiculed the mere thirst for learning <emph rend="i">as learning,</emph>
                    irrespective of application to life, with great liveliness and
                    humour. When he quitted Oxford he proceeded to London, to
                    the Temple, intending to devote himself to the law. Well do I
                    remember how on the very last visit he paid before leaving
                    college, he descanted to me on the advantages he should enjoy in
                    the metropolis, where noble libraries would supply him with every
                    means of prosecuting his literary studies, whilst the association
                    with people of quality would rub off the rust acquired by litera-
                    ture with the rugged tomes of the Statutes at Large. For a time
                    all went on well enough, but the occasional visits to his * people of
                    quality’ soon waxed portentously frequent, till he was at last
                    completely involved in the endless circle of conversaziones, routs,
                    etc., which London designates as social intercourse. There he
                    now is, quite a favourite, of course, and as people say wonderfully
                    improved, but to my way of thinking it’s a wrong sort of improve-
                    ment, to change from grave and taciturn depth to flippant though
                    sparkling shallowmess. I dare say this case of Glaucusis by no
                    means unique. If London then be so * social,* where are we to
                    look, because though at first sight perhaps one would not think
                    so, yet in reality a man can enjoy solitude better there than any-
                    where under the sun, not excepting Salisbury Plain, where the
                    solitude is so deep that it ceases to be solitude. I remember there
                    are two verses somewhere in Childe Harold about this, but alas!
                    memory in common with so much else is base enough to desert a
                    sinking master.</p>
                <p rend="indent(1)">Like nearly all other evils this difficulty of solitude is to be attri-
                    buted, I fancy, to the <emph rend="i">auri sacra fames,</emph> which drives men to and
                    fro in anxious haste with so relentless a goad. But if I get into
                    meditation on this well worn root of evil, I shall make my poor
                    Rose think I have forgotten her, for here I have sate fora whole
                    hour and never spoken to the dear child, so I will e’en put off my
                    thinking cap.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
