<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Modern Hellenism</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Generated by</resp>
                    <name>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Jacob Shelby</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana
                    University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date when="2013">2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>Modern Hellenism</title>
                        <author key="lcnaf">Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909</author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
                            <date when="1857-12">December 1857</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">001</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pp">38-40</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head>MODERN HELLENISM.</head>
                <p>It is no infrequent error of an over-civilized age to depreciate
                    all times and nations, which do not appear either to meet its immediate wants or
                    to be limited by the same theories of action and speculation which confine
                    itself. But this vice of thought is one which we should scarcely expect to find
                    in those who assume the place of guides to the popular opinion, and leaders of
                    the intellect of the day. It proves a narrow and morbid tone of mind, which at
                    once disqualifies a man for occupying any such position.</p>
                <p>We have been lately informed, and that by no slight authority, that
                    the proper work of a Poet as teacher, is to deliver the intellect of his age
                    from all undue influences of habit and example, and to lead it back to purer
                    fountains than slake its daily thirst of knowledge. To do this, we are told, he
                    must be adequate to his time. Thus far, few will dissent from the propositions
                    laid down. But we next discover, that the most perfect instance on record of an
                    age for whom this office was fulfilled by its leaders of thought, is the age of
                        <persName>Pericles</persName>. To substantiate this assertion, we are
                    greeted with the somewhat gratituous information, that it was an age of supreme
                    refinement; a statement which has at least one merit—it is impossible to impugn
                    it. We are, however, left to take it for granted that this quality is, for our's
                    and for all ages, the one supremely desirable and necessary.</p>
                <p><persName>Sophocles</persName> and <persName>Thucydides</persName>
                    are chosen as presenting, on the whole, the most perfect examples of Hellenic
                    intellect; and the inferiority of all other minds is rapidly assumed. The
                    peculiarities of this deified intellect are then discussed with brief eloquence.
                    It is stated to be in cast of thought essentially modern—analytic and inductive
                    in history, serene and graceful in poetry. A parallel is then sketched, we
                    cannot but think with undue haste between the age in question and that of
                        <persName>Elizabeth</persName>. Every Athenian, we are given to understand,
                    possessed a distinct and delicate appreciation of the highest national
                    intellects. The poet and the historian were merely the outcome, each in his own
                    way, of the general popular feeling,—the representatives of somewhat more than
                    the average Greek power of mind—differing, in short, from the mass
                    of the educated people, rather in quantity than in quality of intellect. The
                    Elizabethans, on the other hand, could not produce anything like a man of mind
                    equal to the average ability of Athens. In their best moments the leaders of
                    English thought and action were unable to attain the ordinary height of a
                    Grecian citizen. <persName>Sir Walter Raleigh</persName> is the man selected to
                    prove this assertion. This is at least bold; a man who strikes at
                        <persName>Raleigh</persName> cannot be accused of hawking at small game.</p>
                <p>It is far from the intention of the present writer, even did his
                    space allow it, to enter into an elaborate vindication of
                        <persName>Raleigh</persName>’s character and intellect. The contemptuous
                    laughter of the Oxford theatre will not outweigh the memory of a life, the
                    noblest perhaps among the men of a great age. <persName>Raleigh</persName> in
                    his time outlived worse things than that; <persName>Cecil</persName> and
                        <persName>Coke</persName> were enemies more perilous than an eloquent
                    Professor of the art (or science) of Poetry. To hold him up to the scorn of
                    sciolists and the ridicule of fools, as a mere declaimer on empty questions in
                    an irrational style, may be very amusing—if so, it will not fail of its
                    appropriate reward from the Undergraduate’s gallery— but it will convince no man
                    of the lecturer’s candour or of the force of his argument. If indeed any one
                    seriously desires to see the question of <persName>Raleigh</persName>’s life and
                    its work fully and wisely treated, in a spirit of no irrational reverence, we
                    refer him, certain that he will be in no wise disappointed, to the noble and un-
                    answerable vindication of <persName>Mr. Kingsley.</persName></p>
                <p>But the matter lies far deeper than this. It will require more
                    proof than we have yet received to make us believe that the age which culminated
                    in the yet more shameful than mournful ruin of the Syracusan expedition, was for
                    practical purpose and labour superior to that which attained its consumma- tion
                    in the defeat of the Spanish Armada. Let us see what each age left to its
                    successors. The one, a civilization consumed by sloth and selfishness to the
                    core—the other, a nation so organised as to resist the influence even of Stuart
                    tyranny and Stuart baseness, in the consciousness that under
                        <persName>Elizabeth</persName> it had seen established in Europe, first and
                    for ever, the right of political freedom as the secret of political strength.
                    The one generation, scoffed at by the very poet who helped to brutalize it, left
                    its successors to sink under a disgraceful tyranny; the very recollection of the
                    other paved the way to the establishment of the noblest Republic the world has
                    yet seen. After <persName>Pericles</persName> came <persName>Critias</persName>—
                    after <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, <persName>Cromwell</persName>.</p>
                <p>Let us take the two men respectively offered as specimens.
                        <persName>Raleigh</persName> is no more to be judged solely by his literary
                    works, noble as they are, than his works are to be judged by a few detached
                    passages of inferior importance, which, at worst, can only prove that he saw no
                    further than his rival on points not yet cleared up.* He was the founder of a
                    nation, the valiant and laborious worker in newly-discovered lands, hemmed round
                    with circumstances where he had all to fight against and nothing to uphold him
                    but the 'vivida vis animi';—the resolution of his mighty heart and mind</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">To strive, to seek, to find, and not to yield.</quote>
                <p>To his wise counsel <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, who might have
                    known, attributed in main part the glorious deed of July, 1588.
                        <persName>Thucydides</persName>’ sole campaign was a dishonourable failure.
                    It is not merely unjust—it is simply absurd, to omit all consideration of such
                    facts as these in an elaborate parallel of one man with another. If indeed
                        <persName>Raleigh</persName> be the ancient and
                        <persName>Thucydides</persName> the modern, there is more reason than we had
                    believed in the aspi- ration of minor poets for a time far removed from
                        <quote>'these bad days’, this strange disease of modern life.”</quote></p>
                <p>Was <persName>Bacon</persName> in physical science inferior to the
                    men of the age of <persName>Pericles</persName>? <choice>
                        <orig>was</orig>
                        <corr>Was</corr>
                    </choice> the refined contraction of the Hellenic drama a more adequate type of
                    the generation of <persName>Sophocles</persName>, than
                        <persName>Shakespeare</persName> of the Elizabethans? It may be that we have
                    been hitherto mistaken; but we must have more than the measured rhetoric of a
                    lecture to prove that we must resign the heroes of our own history for the idols
                    of Oxford Hellenism.</p>
                <p><list type="footnotes">
                        <item>The attack is most peculiarly unfair, inasmuch as it represents the
                            histories of <persName>Raleigh</persName> and
                                <persName>Thucydides</persName> as works of like aim, and having
                            first assumed this, proceeds to ridicule the one for being unlike the
                            other.</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
