<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hereditary Influences on Character</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Generated by</resp>
          <name>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Katherine O'Bryan</name>
        </respStmt>   
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana
          University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013">2013</date>  
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title>Hereditary Influences on Character</title>
            <author>Luke</author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
              <date when="1857-12">December 1857</date>
              <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
              <!-- <biblScope type="pp">1-6</biblScope> -->
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="article">
        <p>Peculiar types of countenance, of bodily conformation, and of
          mental and moral characteristics distinguish different nations;
          and these not transient but persistent. From first to last there is
          the same relation between the Athenians and the Spartans, the
          Greeks and the Romans, the English and the French, The
          national activity may be directed to different ends, or some
          restraining power may repress it; but on the whole, the sympathies
          the tastes, the tendencies of a people—all that aggregate of mental
          and moral habits, which is called the character, is perpetuated
          from generation to generation. The circumstances of association,
          training, and the thousand conventionalities of social and political
          life are insufficient to explain and account for this uniformity.
          They explain in many cases the difference between one age and
          another, but they are inadequate to produce a national character
          It is too wide-spread, too deep-rooted : Indeed it is a most curious
          thing to examine into the origin of these circumstances themselves, and
          to watch how very much they are generated and acted upon by
          the different national characters which they seem to create. In
          spite of the changes which have passed over England in the last
          300 years, the race of Englishmen is very much now what it
          was under Elizabetn and the last Henrys. And the slightest
          acquaintance with the present state of Scotland will convince any
          one that the fierce spirit of controversy with which the first Reformers
          assailed the strongholds of false religion and of a truckling aud
          selfish government, combined so strangely as it was with the
          stringent conservatism with which they maintained the truth,
          remain among them to this day, no less than the physical type.</p>
        <p>The same is true always: in all nations there is one continuous
          National Life, It is clear, however, that there must be more than
          merely a general continuity. If this exists, we ought to be able
          to discern the course of the stream, which flows down from age to
          age:—we ought to be able to see its presence as an active power
          amongst ourselves : and this is indeed the fact. Each generation
          grows out of the foregoing, and the children of a house reproduce
          in the main the characters of their parents. As with nations, so
          with families : education and association, powerful as they are,
          cannot account for the whole. Even in the same house, if the
          difference between the parents be at all striking, children grow up,
          all under the same influences, with quite opposite tastes, feelings,
          and tempers.
          The subject presents two very interesting questions. 
          I. The first concerning the influence exercised by the duality
          of the Human Race.
          II. The second, as to the special‘connexion between the mental
          and moral habits of one generation and those of another.</p>
        <p>With reference to the former of these* questions, I believe the
          duality of the race exercises so decided an influence, that it js
          possible, by careful attention to 'the character, and even to the
          expression of countenance, of the individuals whom w,e meet every
          day, to determine whether they represent the Paternal or the
          Maternal element, or whether they combine both. Indeed, it was
          the discovery that I had for some time been unconsciously refer-
          ring many whom I saw to one or other of- these classes that first
          turned my thoughts in this direction.
          On the whole, the Duality is clearly defined: Male and Female;
          Intellectual and Sympathetic; Impressive and Susceptible of
          Impressions; Mechanical and Artistic; Effective and Apprecia-
          tive ; Strong and Weak.
          Taken singly, neither the Masculine nature, nor the Feminine is
          sufficient. The one tends to hardness and narrowness, the other to
          weakness and trifling, nor can either assume the other. The ideal
          of a human creature unites both :—as it is, the finest natures are
          those in which the two are blended. This truth is recognised by
          all unconsciously : we are disappointed if we do not find in a great
          man—even in a great soldier—something of softness and womanly
          tenderness; and we treasure up and repeat stories of such traits
          more than almost any others. In the female character, on the ther hand, 
          it is the union of perfect feminine gentleness with
          something of manly firmness and dignity, that commands our
          admiration. But if the son should represent the father, or the
          daughter the mother for one or more generations, the character
          becomes deteriorated, and the defects of excessive hardness and
          narrowness supervene in the one case, and of excessive weakness
          or frivolity in the other. The natural order of things, if that
          expression may be used in reference to what proves to be the best
          in fact, is that the sons should represent the mother, and the
          daughters should represent the father.</p>
        <p>But when we come to inquire into the special manner in which
          the two elements act, we find ourselves involved in difficulty. To
          take one class alone—that of men who represent the maternal
          element—it is not easy to put into words any set of tests for
          distinguishing them. The classification comes more from an
          undefined feeling, a kind of tact, which escapes us when we seek
          to embody it in language. The grounds of decision are indeed as
          various as are the types of female character ; and the qualities on
          which one man is adjudged to this class may be quite wanting in
          another wTho belongs to it as clearly. In the best specimens, the
          effect produced by the feminine element, appears in their genial
          sympathy with men and nature, giving kindliness to their manners
          and liberality to their thoughts:—in others, the same element is
          found to be the soil and strength of a narrow and timid conserva-
          tism. In some it is the ground of high artistic feelings and
          powers, in others it has frittered away to neatness and anxiety
          about etiquette and personal ornamentation. Sometimes men
          present themselves, of a strangely hard and powerful nature,
          apparently without a touch of womanliness, at the sight of whom,
          nevertheless, the conviction springs up, as it were instinctively,
          and for no reason that appears, that a trace of their mother’s face
          remains in theirs. At the opposite extreme, we find that womanly
          weakness has degenerated into envy, baseness, and crooked dis-
          simulation. From the single eye and the sympathetic mind to
          crooked envy the distance is great—but it is only commensurate
          with the range of female character; and art and language only
          express the general feelirig when they represent the ideal virtues
          and abstractions, as well as the ideal vices under a feminine form.
          It may seem strange that possessing these high qualities
          women should have produced so very little in the departments of Art, Poetry, and Thought. 
          It is possible, however, that though they
          have the power of sympathy, insight, and appreciation, they may
          not have—as is the case—the power of production in an equal
          degree. The chief obstacle, however, is the force of custom, and
          the occupation of their mind with other cares.</p>
        <p>It is unnecessary to dwell on the other exemplifications of the
          influence of the duality of mankind. The distinction is dearly
          marked: the triple division pointed out, exhausts the phrases of
          character: and it is the harmonious interfusion of the two
          elements, taken into connection with the original strength of each,
          that decides the character of nations, 110 less than of individuals.
          In England one is struck by the great preponderance of those in
          whom both elements are blended; and it is, undoubtedly, this
          union of perfect manliness and of somewhat of feminine kindliness
          in the men ; and of perfect womanliness and of somewhat of manly
          self-reliance in the women that is the ground of the pre-eminence
          of Englishmen over all of the existing races. In the French, the
          feminine element seems to prevail to excess—and the fruit is
          excitability, excessive cleverness, frivolity. In the Scots, the
          masculine element preponderates and somewhat narrows and
          hardens the character of the people.</p>
        <p>It becomes, therefore, one test of civilisation to find, out how far
          in any state of society the two are united—how far they are
          divorced. It becomes of national importance to discover whether
          there are any causes at work corrupting either: grinding away
          the gentleness of women by excessive labor* and by want of home
          cares, or turning them to softness and frivolity; and on the other
          hand, whether there is any influence in operation, such as will
          destroy the activity and energy of the men, and turn them to
          effeminacy or indolence; or hardening and brutalizing their
          natures. It is no doubt hard to introduce any essential change
          into a nation’s character, either for the better or the worse. It is as
          difficult as to change the physical type. But there is a limit to the
          persistency both of national character and of the national physical
          type. It is this point which the second question, raised by this
          subject, in part takes up—the question in reference to the special
          connexion between the mental and moral habits of one generation
          and those of another. The fact of the connexion is quite certain.
          Besides many little habits which might possibly be contracted by
          contact, there is a manifest correspondence of tastes, and temper 
          between a child and his parents,—or that parent at least whom it
          chiefly represents. Our attention is drawn mainly to the bad
          qualities—for they unhappily are most conspicuous, and it is
          beyond a doubt, that wiiere the influence of the other parent does
          not neutralise their power, evil temper, base passions, a craving for
          stimulants are handed down from one generation to another.
          Every one knows that mental derangement is hereditary in many
          families: it would be interesting to inquire how far this is owing
          to the transmission of its causes.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, earnest striving after goodness, the fostering
          of a high and holy spirit, under the same conditions descends to
          the second generation—a priceless inheritance.
          In the parents, neither principle is wholly triumphant. In the
          good there is still the struggle against a corrupt will: in the evil,
          the warnings of conscience. The children of the good inherit the
          conquests of their parents: the children of the evil inherit
          unresisted sin. It is born with them—it grows with their growth
          —till a race springs up, like the children of the outcasts of large
          cities, in whom there is no trace of a moral sense.
          Beyond this point, the nature of the subject involves it in much
          obscurity. If we tur,n to the intellectual element, the apparent
          difficulty at once meets us that great men are represented by an
          insignificant race. In reference to this, many reasons might be
          given. It might be said that they ought to be, and indeed are
          represented often, not by their sons, but by their daughters, who
          are not heard of. But in very truth so little can fairly be
          ascertained of what it is that constitutes a great man, whether it is
          not a happy conjunction of qualities which may not readily com-
          bine again, rather than any one remaikable quality, that no conclu-
          sion can well be drawn from them. In point of fact when there is
          any outstanding faculty that is generally reproduced in his
          descendants. To this day the descendants of Maclaurin are
          Mathematicians. But on the whole it 6eems that in so far as the
          one part of man’s nature can be looked on as separate from the
          other, it is the moral and spiritual side of it, the feelings, the
          sympathies, the general habit and constitution of character which
          one generation receives from another. How f£r it even does this
          is not very clear. Passing from the outstanding facts of character
          which were spoken of before,—aspirations after holiness and love
          of sin—it would appear as if we are shut out from knowing more.</p>
        <p>The breast of a man is locked up and none can see it; least of all
          can we see what secret struggles are waged in it between “the
          Spirit and the Flesh,,—nor the hidden sympathy with evil which
          the belter nature or respect to the laws of society constrain men to
          conceal. It is to be remembered, however, that these are not the
          less in the nature of the man : not the less do they enter into the
          first nature of the children; who, according to the character of
          their parents, grow up with a stronger power to resist sin, or a
          stronger tendency to embrace it.</p>
        <p>r. Helps in one of his later essays observes, that if it were
          only for selfish reasons a man should do all that is in his power
          to reform the waste places of great cities: for no man can tell how
          soon his own descendants may be brought down to them. This
          is capable of extension. It is right and well that men and women
          should attend to such things; it is right also that in the good
          things of this world they should make provision for those that
          come after them. But this is not all: a pure heart and a sound
          mind is an inheritance quite incommensurate in value even on the
          lowest considerations with a great estate. Vices bring want:
          honesty brings riches and honor. It is more rational then, first to
          seek to provide these ; by striving to extirpate in a man's own
          heart all sympathy with evil and to foster all that is good. Of a
          certainty the fruit will appear ; and whatever disturbing agencies
          there are, the result, as in the case of any other general law,
          will be the natural outgrowth of the cause. When we hear of
          God’s blessing and anger resting upon the “ children's children”;
          it is in this general law of the development of good and evil, as
          they pass from one generation to another, that we are to look for
          its fulfilment.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>