<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Louis Napoleon Part I</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Generated by</resp>
                    <name>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Jacob Shelby</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana
                    University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date when="2013">2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>Louis Napoleon Part I</title>
                        <author key="lcnaf">Nichol, John, 1833-1894</author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
                            <date when="1857-12">December 1857</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">001</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pp">31-37</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head>LOUIS NAPOLEON. Part I.</head>
                <p>The events which fill up the annals of France during the last sixty
                    years, or since the period of the great revolution, are indeed all of a kind
                    that would seem to prohibit our connecting the idea of permanence with any form
                    of government that for the time may be there established.</p>
                <p>No country perhaps ever within so short a time underwent changes so
                    frequent, so sudden, so strange. From a republic with certain guarantees for
                    freedom, and a basis in entire social equality, France rushed at once under <hi
                        rend="i">sans culotte</hi> domination: then she emerged into the glory
                    and despotism of the first Empire: then hailed the return of the Bourbons as an
                    advent: in 1830 ignominiously expelling that same elder branch, and for ever
                    renouncing the principle of legitimacy, the country accepted and installed the
                    constitutional monarchy of <persName>Louis Philippe</persName>, an astute and
                    moderate though not a generous sovereign; redescend- ing in 1848 by the steep of
                    the barricades towards an impossible republic, she flaunted the tricolor for two
                    years: and now again she has established an empire, adopting as its symbol that
                    wonderful name which carried her victorious eagles nearly over the world. It is
                    of course not permissible that from the mere existence of changes like
                    these—from this long prevalence of instability—we infer that France must change
                    again and never attain to a suitable and irreversible rule: regularity of
                    sequence during the past, unless it is <hi rend="i">unconditioned</hi> and
                    its terms directly joined in <hi rend="i">causality</hi>, being no safe
                    ground of expectation that a similar course will characterise the future:
                    nevertheless it is not to be overlooked, that in the simple fact of <hi
                        rend="i">such catastrophes having been</hi> there is one element of
                    serious peril to all regular or continuous government, and the ground therefore
                    of what we may term an apriori probability against the assured stability of any
                    dynasty in that country, whatever its intrinsic merits.</p>
                <p>At every epoch and at every stage of social progress, the
                    permanence of public order must greatly depend, in every country, on the
                    existence among its people of a habit of obedience and of respect for the Laws.
                    Attribute the largest possible significance and the widest application to the
                    maxim that Govornment draws its strongest sanctions and its surest support from
                    the assent or contentment of the governed, it were yet vain and chimerical to
                    expect that, in the most enlightened republic on which sun ever shone, every man
                    of those masses from whom obedience is necessary can become satisfied with the
                    details of every enactment which commands them; nor indeed has any govern- ment
                    ever succeeded in repressing turbulence, unless through tacit reliance on the
                    reverence for its ordinances which springs out of habitual submission and the
                    indisposition unnecessarily to alter its laws.</p>
                <p>Sudden breaks in the course of social order accordingly have always
                    been dreaded by the prudent; and when, through para- mount exigencies, they
                    could not be evaded, they have always brought danger, even to the stablest and
                    most moderate of nations. Few we believe will now gainsay the assertion that the
                    great English rebellion under <persName>Cromwell</persName> was demanded by the
                    highest interests of these realms, and became, under providence, the efficient
                    cause of that settlement of British liberty under <persName>William of
                        Orange</persName> in 1688. Neither is it question- able that the reigns of
                        <persName>William</persName>William and his successors were wise,
                    conciliatory, and in every way worthy of British princes; nevertheless history
                    presents, in the annals of these years, a succession of endless and bitter
                    intrigues, envenomed con- spiracies, fruitless and hopeless revolts ; in so much
                    that a just historical criticism will ever attribute the establishment of
                    constitutional principles in England not more to the con- federacy that expelled
                    the worthless Stewarts, than to the wary and resolute statesmanship which, in
                    succeeding reigns, brought back the ancient habits of our people and repaired
                    their confidence in stability. If then even the solid and sagacious Anglo Saxon
                    did not escape unscathed through the turbulence Of one revolution, how shall we
                    estimate the damage endured by an element so essential to stability, because of
                    that succession of disastrous overthrows which have well nigh banished all just
                    conception of the value of order, from the naturally unstable, impulsive, and
                    impetuous French.</p>
                <p>They have sunk, it is to be greatly feared, into an utter anta-
                    gonism to all order—<hi rend="i">the very habit of instability</hi>—they
                    seem now disposed to overturn a government with as little hesitation, and for <choice>
                        <orig>ns</orig>
                        <corr>as</corr>
                    </choice> little reason as one would alter his dress or shift his house; and
                    this unhappy propensity to change is aggravated by a vain- glory, which
                    persuades them that France is in the van of Europe —Europe, which if one may
                    judge from what has occurred within the experience of a lifetime in Spain,
                    Italy, Hungary, and not long ago over the length and breadth of Germany, may
                    herself any day break from her moorings, and enter without rudder or pilot on
                    the tempestuous ocean of Revolution.</p>
                <p>We must, however, look below the mere external fact of the
                    frequency of those changes. Let me ask what canker in the constitution of French
                    society has permitted change to become so frequent, what disease it is which has
                    enabled <hi rend="i">instability</hi> to take the place in that country,
                    of <hi rend="i">order</hi>; whether the disease be an accidental or an
                    inherent one, and whether, independently even of vicious habits engendered by
                    the past, there is besides an efficient cause which may thus unhappily likewise
                    influence the future. Unfortunately phenomena of this description are not
                    strange to History. As one emphatic illustration, look to Rome at the period of
                    her Emperors. Probably the annals of the world contain no more astonishing
                    instance of an utter instability, as to the persons or dynasty occupying there
                    the supreme power. No fewer than eleven Emperors succeeded each other from
                        <persName>Claudius</persName> to <persName>Hadrian</persName>, in the
                    lifetime of <persName>Juvenal</persName> alone: of these five were murdered, one
                    driven to suicide, another virtually died through effect of insult and dread:
                    the <hi rend="i">suprema dies</hi> came to three only,
                        <persName>Vespasian</persName>, <persName>Titus</persName>, and
                        <persName>Trajan</persName>, in a natural manner. Of later times yet more
                    startling and terrible the records; and indeed most woeful the contrast <choice>
                        <orig>wtih</orig>
                        <corr>with</corr>
                    </choice> that firm and glorious state ruled by its senate, that indeed had its
                    intestine dangers, and was sometimes humbled in war, but yet in spite of
                        <persName>Cataline</persName> or Carthaginian, which stood erect like a
                    granite mountain, its base fixed as on some pillar of the world. Now we shall
                    find, on due inquiry, that one common social characteristic prevailed in Rome,
                    in those days as in France now—nay that this one characteristic distinguishes
                    all such epochs, establishes among them a natural analogy, and has given
                    opportunity to their revolutions. Rome passed from the Republic to the Empire,
                    precisely as France passed from the old monarchy, <hi rend="i">through an
                        ordeal which destroyed utterly every vestige of independent local
                        government, and wholly centralized its system of administration.</hi></p>
                <p>To prevent mistakes let us state briefly what the principle of
                    local government within a State really is, and what it necessarily effects for
                    the stability of that state. A local government, as we now speak of it, is
                    simply a source or seat of independent power restricted it may be but still
                    independent—obtaining therefore its share of the respects of the people, and a
                    portion of their feality. It is of little consequence what is the form of this
                    local government, provided it be real and <choice>
                        <orig>independant</orig>
                        <corr>independent</corr>
                    </choice>. It may, for instance, consist in municipalities, whose rights are
                    secured by charters: it may take the form it has in America, of sovereign though
                    restricted local legislations; or, as is the case oftenest, it may be exercised
                    by a national Aristocracy, distinguished by rank and wealth—each member of which
                    wields a national influence as well as his delegated powers. Securing various
                    degrees of liberty, every one of these forms necessarily ensures a high degree
                    of social stability. By being almost in contact with the people, the local
                    governor naturally excites an amount of practical attachment which cannot be
                    hoped for by remoter power: and, depending in his turn on the central power,
                    every such governor with the amount of social influence that surrounds him is a
                    natural support of the state. It is to such a state of the body politic that the
                    name <hi rend="i">social pyramid</hi> has its peculiar applicability. The
                    sovereign authority is there the apex or copstone of a scheme of hierarchies,
                    morticed into each other and slowly tapering upwards from the broad basis of the
                    nation: whereas authority absolute and unassociated has its similtude in that
                    old symbol of insolent power which aroused the heroic Tell, a bare pole
                    surmounted by some Austrian hat at the mercy of every passing storm. The
                    aristocracy of old Rome extinct, her municipalities bereft of reality, her
                    provincial governments at the nod of any favourite slave, what mattered the name
                    or descent of the master. Who beyond the city’s walls cared though the Lords of
                    the world were the wretches of whom <persName>Juvenal</persName> and
                        <persName>Tacitus</persName> wrote; or, if indeed they cared, how many in
                    the Empire had the power and therefore the desire to remonstrate, when they
                    heard of a murder or deposition, or a fresh shout from the venal
                    praetorians?</p>
                <p>It is the curse of all governments of this kind that altho’ they
                    produce slavishness in the extreme, towards an existing holder of power, they
                    have no natural mode of engendering attachment to the man or respect for his
                    dynasty. So long as the purple enwraps him he has worshippers enow; but let the
                    sceptre nod or the fingers that grasp it relax, let accident menace or con-
                    spiracy be successful, and straightway the ears of the deserted oppressor are
                    assailed by the howling of that same degraded band, which now drowns the cries
                    of the oppressed.</p>
                <p>Thus is there no strength or natural endurance in that show of
                    subservient pomp, which alone can surround a <persName>Louis
                    Napoleon</persName>. There is a certain Prefect of Toulouse who, on a late
                    occasion, hailed his usurpation as a new advent of <persName>Messiah</persName>:
                    he had done for <persName>Louis Philippe</persName> as much in a similar
                    direction as the saner mind of that monarch could bear; and if the pitiful
                    sycophant lives, his adulation will be as impious at the feet of the yet unseen
                    agency that shall overthrow the Empire.</p>
                <p>Such the general results forced upon us, by all recent experience
                    of France, by the analogy of History, and the surest tenets of social
                    philosophy. The question remains with what probability of success shall the
                    Empire under <persName>Louis Napoleon</persName> struggle against odds which
                    thus lie so fearfully opposing it?</p>
                <p>The disorganized and unsettled state of the public mind—now grown
                    almost into a <hi rend="i">habit of disorder</hi>, has removed from under
                    every ruler in our neighbouring country that primal security on which states
                    repose; and the description of power, required to be propped up, we have found
                    to be necessarily the unstablest of all those forms of government of whose fates
                    we possess any record. Are there then counterbalancing
                    circumstances—circumstances which shall overbear those unfavourable chances,
                    either in the present peculiar condition of France or in the character of the
                    man who has siezed her throne.</p>
                <p>Now it is not to be denied that there is a craving on the part of
                    many of the influential classes in that country for the permanence of order of
                    some kind; and it is perfectly true that men of property were frightened more
                    than enough by that effusion of wretched and impracticable economical schemes,
                    which characterized the era of the late short lived republic. <choice>
                        <orig>Nevertheles</orig>
                        <corr>Nevertheless</corr>
                    </choice>, it were utterly erroneous to confuse this loyalty of the
                    stock-exchange with loyalty to Napoleon or his house, to expect from it fidelity
                    under reverse, or even assistance in serious peril. Power of any kind, so long
                    as it exists unmenaced, will have support and acclamation from many quarters;
                    but there is no description of conservatism whose fealty is of so easy
                    transference as this conversatism of mere wealth. There is but feeble gallantry
                    in money bags. The question shall we kick <persName>Sejanus</persName>, or shall
                    we kick <persName>Tiberius</persName>, is in the conscience of the three
                    percents, synonymous with the question whether is <persName>Tiberius</persName>
                    or <persName>Sejanus</persName> the uppermost? Let but the idol be on the
                    throne, the stocks are subservient—ready, according to the expressive phrase of
                        <persName>Tacitus</persName>,<quote>' rucre in servitium !'</quote> No
                    matter for the <choice>
                        <orig>villianies</orig>
                        <corr>villainies</corr>
                    </choice> through which he has strod, or that his seat is on crushed liberty—so
                    be it that the funds may rise: and <hi rend="i">our</hi> times have
                    blushed at the spectacle of rich men, grave men, free men forgetting the dignity
                    and reserve of Britons, and, with extra- vagant incaution, almost overstepping
                    the limits of law, for the privilege of kneeling at his footstool.* We set aside
                    then as a source of independent conservative action, and as of no real bearing
                    on the question we are discussing, all these present claims of <persName>Louis
                        Napoleon</persName> on the hearts of the monied interest. If the analogies
                    of history do not singularly fail they will serve him little as a defence
                    against any form of change, which is seriously threatened.</p>
                <p>Reverting therefore to the general foundations of his power, let us
                    ask how far <hi rend="i">they</hi> are likely to come into successful
                    collision with important social forces, already efficient or sure to be
                    developed in France? Now as to what these foundations are, it is fortunate there
                    can be no mistake. A wit the other day advertised by <persName>Napoleon the
                        Third</persName>, a work on the principles of mild and rational
                    government,—the said principles being set forth in five chapters, headed
                    Artillery, Infantry, Cavalry, Police, and Priests! I shall not enter upon his
                    various reduction to practice of these several cunning instruments; but I
                    suppose it may be said without fear of contradiction, that a despotism more
                    thoroughly centralized, more inimical to free individual action, or individual
                    developement of any kind, has never before existed in Europe. Through all France
                    at this moment there is not an administrative officer who dare anything else
                    than the slave of the Imperial Minister of Police. Repre- sentative Assemblies
                    are an open mockery at the Tuilleries; the press is gagged, mens' words even are
                    watched, and but the other day the people were forbidden to gather in respect
                    around the bier of their lyrist <persName>B<hi rend="accent">e</hi>ranger</persName>, 
                    The great <persName>Napoleon</persName> also sneered 
                    <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>Referring to the embassy of London Merchants in the year 1853.</item>
                    </list> at idealogues; he too desired to extinguish freedom, but he could place
                    his own glory in its stead. Shall the enterprize he ultimately failed in, be
                    achieved by the little <persName>Napoleon</persName>, who has nothing wherewith
                    to dazzle Frenchman, but the shade of a name and in the shape of a hat? For the
                    approaching years in that country there is but a simple alternative. If France
                    be unfortunate—if prosperity, through whatever actual causes, yield to adversity
                    and its discontents, it is easy to see that a government so weak through its
                    novelty, and which has ostentatiously assumed the responsibility of the entire
                    fate of the country, will be made to bear the burden of that responsibility;—one
                    under which no such government can ever stand. If on the other hand, if
                    auspicious circumstances induce the prolongation of prosperity, then the <choice>
                        <orig>developement</orig>
                        <reg>development</reg>
                    </choice> alike of the material and intellectual energies of France will be
                    found too strong for any despotism. It is a peculiarity of the civilization, of
                    the modern world—that character in fact which most of all distinguishes it from
                    the civilizations of antiquity—that, as it is based on productive and commercial
                    industry, it cannot reach any high degree without bringing up along with it, to
                    a proportionate level, the sense of individual independence and attachment to
                    personal rights. Successful labor is at bottom the most indestruct- ible power
                    in our modern world; and hence all prosperous modern states tend more or less
                    towards democracies. It is thus, too most essentially, with our modern
                    literature, which in the main is an expression of the sympathies of the
                    independent industrial class. Even in the palmiest days of its monarchy the
                    literature of France was emphatically democratic. Its vivacity, its wit, its
                    irrepressible sarcasm, its fearless speculation are known as among the chief of
                    the agencies which brought that long and glorious monarchy to the dust; and it
                    must be through causes of which no trace is apparent now, than for more than a
                    brief season it can be denuded of its old spirit, and resisted as a
                    revolutionary power. This new <persName>Caligula</persName> may banish all who
                    speak of tyrants, he can stifle, but for a time that energy, which will remain
                    silent at the bidding neither of police nor priest.</p>
                <p rend="i">(To be continued)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
