<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Early English Dramatists</title>
                <editor>John A. Walsh</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Steven Heinen</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp>Encoding checked and edited by</resp>
                  <name>John A. Walsh</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Culture Lab, Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date when="2013">2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>The Early English Dramatists</title>
                        <author>Christopher Marlowe &amp; John Webster</author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
                            <date when="1857-12">December 1857</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">001</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pp">7-15</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <tagsDecl>	
          <!-- Basic text formatting: bold, italic, underline, "normal," etc. -->
          <rendition xml:id="b" n="tiebp:bold" scheme="css">
            font-weight:bold;
          </rendition> 
          
          <rendition xml:id="i" n="tiebp:italic" scheme="css">
            font-style:italic;
          </rendition> 
          
          <rendition xml:id="u" n="tiebp:underline" scheme="css">
            text-decoration:underline;
          </rendition> 
          
          <rendition xml:id="n" n="teibp:normal" scheme="css">
            font-weight:normal;
            text-decoration:none;
            font-style:normal;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="mono" n="teibp:mono" scheme="css">
            font-family:Monaco,Courier,monospace;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="super" n="tiebp:super" scheme="css">
            vertical-align:super;
            font-size:80%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="sub" n="tiebp:sub" scheme="css">
            vertical-align:sub;
            font-size:80%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="lowercase" n="tiebp:lowercase" scheme="css">
            text-transform:lowercase;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="uppercase" n="tiebp:uppercase" scheme="css">
            text-transform:uppercase;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="capitalize" n="tiebp:capitalize" scheme="css">
            text-transform:capitalize;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="small-caps" n="tiebp:small-caps" scheme="css">
            font-variant:small-caps;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Blocks. -->
          <rendition xml:id="block" n="tiebp:block" scheme="css">
            display:block;
          </rendition> 
          <rendition xml:id="block-margins" n="teibp:block-margins" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            margin-top:1em;
            margin-bottom:1em;
          </rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="blockquote" n="tiebp:blockquote" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            font-size:90%;
            margin-left:3em;
            padding-left:1em;
            border-left: 1px solid gray;
            margin-top:.75em;
            margin-bottom:.75em;
            padding-top:.75em;
            padding-bottom:.75em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition corresp="#blockquote" n="tiebp:blockquote" scheme="css" scope="before">
            <!-- This turns off the default generated quotes for block quotes. -->
            content:"" !important;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition corresp="#blockquote" n="tiebp:blockquote" scheme="css" scope="after">
            <!-- This turns off the default generated quotes for block quotes. -->
            content:"" !important;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="codeblock" n="teibp:codeblock" scheme="css">
            display: block;
            font-size: 80%;
            margin-left: 1em;
            padding-left: 1em;
            border-left: 1px solid gray;
            margin-top: .75em;
            margin-bottom: .75em;
            padding-top: .75em;
            padding-bottom: .75em;
            font-family:Monaco,Courier,monospace;
            white-space:pre;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Inline -->
          
          <rendition xml:id="inline" n="teibp:inline" scheme="css">
            display:inline;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Alignment. -->
          <rendition xml:id="center" n="tiebp:center" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            text-align:center;
            margin-left:auto;
            margin-right:auto;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="left" n="teibp:left" scheme="css">
            text-align:left;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="right" n="teibp:right" scheme="css">
            text-align:right;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="justify" n="teibp:justify" scheme="css">
            text-align:justify;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="center-block" n="tiebp:center-block" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            margin-left:auto;
            margin-right:auto;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Indentation -->
          <rendition xml:id="hang" n="teibp:hang" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:2.5em;
            text-indent:-2.5em;
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- Indentation for verse lines. Results in a “hanging” indent if
					the line wraps. -->
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-01" n="tiebp:l-indent-01" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:4em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-02" n="tiebp:l-indent-02" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:6em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-03" n="tiebp:l-indent-03" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:8em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-04" n="tiebp:l-indent-04" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:10em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-05" n="tiebp:l-indent-05" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:12em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-06" n="tiebp:l-indent-06" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:14em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-07" n="tiebp:l-indent-07" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:16em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="l-indent-08" n="tiebp:l-indent-08" scheme="css">
            display:block;
            padding-left:18em;
            text-indent:-2em;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="indent" n="tiebp:indent" scheme="css" scope="before">
            /* text-indent:4em; */
            /* The above method of describing an indentation for, say, a paragraph is preferred.
            The method being used is in response to a bug in some browsers whereby a block
            element, like a paragraph, is erroneously re-indented after interruption by another 
            block element (like a list, which is valid inside a paragraph). */
            content:"\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0";
          </rendition>
          
          <!-- font sizes -->
          
          <rendition xml:id="small" n="tiebp:small" scheme="css">
            font-size:90%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="x-small" n="tiebp:x-small" scheme="css">
            font-size:85%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="xx-small" n="tiebp:xx-small" scheme="css">
            font-size:80%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="large" n="tiebp:large" scheme="css">
            font-size:110%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="x-large" n="tiebp:x-large" scheme="css">
            font-size:115%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="xxx-large" n="tiebp:xxx-large" scheme="css">
            font-size:120%;
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition xml:id="bracket" n="teibp:bracket" scheme="css"/>
          
          <rendition corresp="#bracket" n="tiebp:bracket" scheme="css" scope="before">
            content:"&lt;";
          </rendition>
          
          <rendition corresp="#bracket" n="tiebp:bracket" scheme="css" scope="after">
            content:">";
          </rendition>
        </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head>The Early English Dramatists</head>
                <p>In the dramatists of the Elizabethan period and their immediate
                    successors, there are certain salient points of resemblance which
                    no imitation has been able to reproduce, except in a faint and
                    faded mimicry. From the mighty line of <persName>Marlowe</persName> to the glitter
                    and point of <persName>Shirley</persName>, a sort of unity may be discerned in all the
                    productions of those old writers, among whom Shakespeare
                    moved only as greatest of many great. Unity in variety; for
                    there is no servile adherence to one standard, no blind
                    conformity to one stock of rules. Still, all the plays of this era
                    are coloured by the same influences, and modelled by the same
                    tone of national thought and feeling. Till the siren-like music of
                    <persName>Beaumont</persName> and <persName>Fletcher</persName>, 
                    nothing of artificial sentiment or 
                    frostwork ornament overlaid the power and purity which clothed in
                    words the lofty actions and profound passions of their drama.
                    The writers above-named, with all their varied and brilliant
                    merit, were the first to mix with the very sources of poetry that
                    faint, false sweetness which enervates the mind and cloys the taste
                    of the reader. In this perhaps, as much as by their more
                    glaring errors, the influence of their plays did much to weaken
                    and lower the tone of the generation which followed and worshipped 
                    them. It is with earlier poets, with minds more strong
                    and fresh, from which the stamp of a stern and glorious age was
                    not yet outworn, that we have now to do. I propose to-day to
                    give as fair an account as will come within a range so limited, of
                    two among these whom I consider wormiest of attention,
                    <persName>Marlowe</persName> and <persName>Webster</persName>. The latter, indeed, in strict chronology,
                    might perhaps be classed with writers of the second period ; his
                    works are as certainly later in date than <persName>Marlowe</persName>'s, as prior to those
                    of <persName>Beaumont</persName> and <persName>Fletcher</persName>: but the tone of his writings would
                    be enough to rank him as a dramatist of the earlier class, if
                    indeed a remarkable testimony of his preference for the school of
                    Shakespeare did not remain under his own hand, in the preface to
                    the first of his great tragedies. I shall, therefore, without
                    scruple assign him a place among the poets of the first era, rather
                    than with those of whom Beaumont and Fletcher were the chief
                    leaders, and among whom we may class <persName>Shirley</persName>, <persName>Massinger</persName>, and
                    their followers.
                </p>
                <p>Between the two great writers whom I have chosen for
                    examination, there are many points of likeness and many of
                    diversity. Both have a more subtle and profound power of
                    analyzing the nature of man in its height and depth, in its strength
                    and weakness, than (with one exception) was possessed by any of
                    their contemporaries. Both have a fondness for gloom and
                    shadow, which in less powerful minds would have sunk into a
                    morbid lust of horror and pain. Their scenes, as it is, inflict no
                    base emotion of shallow terror or mean suffering, such as weak
                    writers who would fain be strong endeavour to excite, that so,
                    while concealing their inherent weakness and want of faith in art
                    they may at least harrow the nerves and crush the feelings of
                    readers feeble as themselves.
                </p>
                <p>Both have a perfect and facile command of language; it
                    obeys them as a willing slave; each thought is married to a fit
                    expression. To each of these poets it is always an aim to strip
                    naked every passion of all its form and circumstances and hold it
                    up, bad or good, as it is in very truth. Neither has the slightest
                    respect for anything like a sham, poetical or otherwise: another
                    material difference between their writings and the elaborate
                    luxuriance of the later school. Their style has the simple and
                    noble outlines of the great early painters of Italy and Flanders:
                    <persName>Fletcher</persName>’s is ornate and melodious, artificial in its very effusion,
                    coloured and toned down in its very passion, with all the calculated
                    effects and measured theatricalism of the eclectics.
                </p>
                <p><persName>Marlowe</persName> has more of pure unmingled poetry in his composition
                    than <persName>Webster</persName>; he is glad of any chance that allows him to
                    indulge in musical expression and a certain tender glory of
                    description which makes every line a picture and a song in itself:
                    in his fellow-dramatist, the poetry of expression only appears
                    when forced forth by passion—never as an ornamental adjunct,
                    always as a necessary part of the situation: a great and rare merit,
                    which make it hopeless to give au idea of his power unless by
                    excerpts of considerable length. Throughout <persName>Marlowe</persName>'s works
                    there is a passionate love and worship of beauty, which in
                    <persName>Webster</persName> gleams out by comparatively dim and scanty indications.
                    Not indeed that the latter is deficient in the sense of enjoyment; he
                    reposes now and then in sweet intervals as of music; and we meet
                    with such harmonious touches of expression as in the following
                    lines:—
                </p>
                <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                    
                    <lg>
                        
                        <l rendition="#l-indent-6">Untie your folded thoughts,</l>
                        
                        <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And let them dangle loose as a bride’s hair.</l>
                    </lg>  
                </quote>
                <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">O, thou soft natural death, that art joint twin</l>
                        
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">To sweetest slumber! no rough bearded comet</l>
                        
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Stares on’thy mild departure ; the dull owl</l>  
                    
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Beats not against thy casement; the hoarse wolf</l> 
                    
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Scents not thy carrion; pity winds thy corpse,</l> 
                    
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Whilst horror waits on princes.</l> 
                </quote>
                
                <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                    
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-8">One whose mind</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Appears more like a ceremonious chapel,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Full of sweet music, than a thronging presence.</l>
                
                </quote>
                
                <p>Such passages might be easily multiplied, had I space for &amp;
                complete analysis; but these may suffice to show the tender grace
                and earnest harmony of style with which a poet of true dramatic
                genius finds time to soften the tragedy cf any subject. He will
                never urge terror beyond its due limits, or forget in the hurry and
                passion of circumstance the beauty which should ever move as
                naturally round his thoughts as its splendour round the motion of
                a star.
                </p>
                <p>It remains to consider in what measure each of these writers
                has fulfilled the main requisitions of the dramatic art And
                here I must notice the chief defect of <persName>Marlowe</persName>. His dramas
                usually lag in the action; sometimes the original interest is dropped
                midway, and the artistic significance of the whole work destroyed.
                Into no such error does <persName>Webster</persName> ever fall: but it is fair to
                remember that he had lived to study the most perfect models
                of the dramatic art. The latter's pathos is, in my opinion, more
                subtle and intense than has been attained by any other of our dramatists
                but <persName>Shakespeare</persName> and <persName>Shelley</persName> : a quality in which I cannot but
                    think <persName>Marlowe</persName> comparatively deficient. None ever went beyond
                him in power and beauty of words; no one could have drawn in
                firmer outline the scenes of suffering which he loved to lay bare
                before his readers: but any one of the three dramatists I have
                mentioned would have steeped them in a deeper pathos and
                glorified them with a purer compassion. There is a divine pity
                and love in some great poets which crowns their completed art as
                with a halo of sacred sorrow. This is not in <persName>Marlowe</persName>; scorn,
                and a fierce delight in his own power and skill, have driven
                out all mercy; others may pity the agony he exhibits, but in him
                is no compassion. His is the strength that cannot pardon
                weakness; the realism that will veil nothing, explain nothing
                away. There is something terrible in his quiet, pitiless dissection
                of character, his silent scrutiny into all dark and dubious points
                of circumstance, his steady self-confidence in handling the
                forbidden and the fearful; his foot slips not, his eye falters not,
                on the narrow verge of life; where all darkest questions meet and
                mingle, in religious and ethical speculation, in moral and spiritual
                doubts, there has he been, a cold and keen enquirer; the
                sensuous passion of his temperament subdued and subservient to
                the judicial will.	All these questions has he	faced without
                wavering: no influence has bowed him this way or that; and he
                returns unable, perhaps undesirous, to settle the perplexities of
                faith and conduct. Such at least seems to me the moral underlying
                his life and works.
                </p>
                <p>And	yet, with	all	his faults of speculation and action—
                for this confusion	of	moral boundaries and hard contempt of
                human	wants is	a	grave error enough—how	did he keep
                unaltered and unsoiled his name and rank as a poet! In his
                tragedies, as before stated, we find no less of that* sensuous and
                passionate’ beauty which lies at the very inmost core of his power,
                than in the rapid rhythms and gorgeous luxuries of his Hero and
                Leander. In that poem, indeed, he seems to have put off all
                other claims to praise, only to abandon himself in utter freedom to
                the enjoyments of music and colour. The passion of the lovers
                is a thin veil for that of the poet; it goes no deeper than external
                delight; but by a beautiful use of his realizing and analytic style
                he has done justice once for all to that much misused and belied
                thing, the purely sensuous and outward side of love. And from
                the very excess of pleasureable emotion, which burns and
                trembles thro’ the verse as a flower trembles open to the
                air, the whole poem is thrown back into some remote
                visionary land, which cannot affect or alter any human relation.
                It is not the love that we are conscious of, but the enjoyment only.
                The same, in a modified degree, may be said of Shakespeare's
                Venus and Adonis,—a poem of the same character as the present,
                but so tempered by the peculiar properties of its author as to rank
                far above all others of the same school.
                </p>
                <p>Another point of contrast requires notice:	the terrors of
                    <persName>Webster</persName>'s drama are, for the most part, purely spiritual; those of
                    <persName>Marlowe</persName>'s, often tainted by the intrusion of mere physical
                endurance: which latter, when lifted by no sentiment beyond its
                own relations, it is of itself unfit for dramatic treatment. There is a
                truth in the old Greek theories which bade poets avoid all horrible
                exposure in their writings, and be careful of turning the exceptional
                into the repulsive. This dogma, pushed to the extreme, leaves us
                a tragedy bound in grave-clothe, with a nerveless whine for voice
                and a draped lay-figure for study ; the clear eyes blinded with a
                fool’s bandage, the mighty music and measured thunder as of the
                choral heavens, changed for an emasculated and sickly drawl.
                But poets far above the so-called 1 classic school, have erred as
                gravely on the other hand. Art is not dissection: nothing is
                more offensive than bare and sensuous horror. Spiritual suffering
                in every detail and symptom belongs to the, large dowry, of art;
                but not the details of the slaughter-house. The noble censure
                passed by Mr. Ruskin, on the painters of foul and bloody scenes,
                the art whose place is in the kennel or the shambles, applies
                equally to the poet who defiles his pow£r in the same way. I do
                not accuse either <persName>Marlowe</persName> or <persName>Webster</persName> of this hideous lust of
                pain; I have already expressed my belief in their healthy and
                vigorous purity of purpose, and I desire here to assert it again.
                Nevertheless, there" is in <persName>Marlowe</persName> a suspicion of this fatal
                tendency; had he been a weaker man, it might have widened into
                a serious defect. Compare, for specimens of different treatment,
                the death-scene of <persName>Marlowe</persName>'s Edward II. with that of <persName>Webster</persName>'s
                Duchess of Malfi.
                </p>
                <p>To atone for all this inadequate praise and presumptous censure
                    take two specimens’ of <persName>Marlowe</persName>'s power of subtle thought and
                    delicate expression; the first pure speculation, as the second is
                    pure description:—</p>
                </div>
                <div type="poem">
                <head>Theory of Beauty.</head>
                
                <quote type="blockquote"> 
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">If all the pens that ever poets held</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Had fed the feeling of their masters* thoughts,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And every sweetness that inspired their hearts,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Their win Is, and muses on admired themes;</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">If all the heavenly quintessence they still</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">From their immortal flowers of poesy,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Wherein as in a mirror we perceive</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">The highest reaches of a human wit;</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">If these had made one poem’s period,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And all combined iu beanty’s worthiness,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Yet should there hover in their restless heads</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">One thought, one grace, one wonder, at the least,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Which into words no virtue can digest”</l>
                </quote>
                </div>
            <div type="poem">
                <head><persName>Faust</persName> evokes the shape of <persName>Helen</persName>.</head>
                
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Was this the face that launched a thousand ships</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And burnt the topless towers of lliam?</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Sweet <persName>Helen</persName>, make me immortal with a kiss.</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Her lips suck forth my soul, see where it flies!</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Come, <persName>Helen</persName>, come, give me my soul again.</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Here will 1 dwell, for Heaven is in these lips,</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And all is dross that is not <persName>Helena</persName>,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">I will be Paris, and for love of thee</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Instead of Troy shall Wurtemberg be sacked</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And I will combat with weak Menelaus,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And wear thy colours on my plumed crest:</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Yea, I will wound <persName>Achilles</persName> in -the heel,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And then return to Helen for a kiss.</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">O, thou art fairer than the evening air,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Clad in the beauty of a thousand stars:</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Brighter art thou than flaming Jupiter</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">When he appeared to hapless Semele;</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">More lovely than the monarch of the sky</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">In wanton Arethusa's azured arms;</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">And none but thou shalt be my paramour!”</l>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <p>Observe especially, besides the sensuous perfection of language,
                    the passionate will expressed in this passage by the earnest
                    repetition of the mere words ‘I' and 'thou': as if the sorcerer
                    feared that at the least relaxation of his wilful and potent desire, his</p>
            </div>
                <div type="poem">
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Compare an earlier passage in the same tragedy:</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Spirits—like women or unwedded maids,</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Shadowing more beauty in their airy brows</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Than have the white breasts of the Queen of love.</l>
                    
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">Compare <persName>Shakespeare</persName>'s,</l>
                    <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                        <l rendition="#l-indent-6">White and azure, laced</l>
                        <l rendition="#l-indent-4">With blue of heaven's own tint,</l>
                    </quote>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2">(Where see <persName>Mr. Knight</persName>’s excellent note,) and</l>
                    <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                        <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Her two blue windows faintly she upheaveth.</l>
                    </quote>
                    <p><persName>Venus</persName>and<persName>Adonis</persName></p>
                 
                </div>
                <div type="article">
                <p>influence might cease and the vision foil him after all. He is afraid
                    to believe her a mere creature of his will, and half dreams that the
                    spells which evoked may retain her for ever as a real and breathing
                    woman at his side.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <p>influence might cease and the vision foil him after all. He is afraid
                    to believe her a mere creature of his will, and half dreams that the
                    spells which evoked may retain her for ever as a real and breathing
                    woman at his side.</p>
                <p>A few words more of <persName>Webster</persName>, to whom alone far more
                    than all my space should be given to do justice; what remains,
                    must be comprised in a few brief remarks. His two great
                    works, <persName>Vittoria Corombona</persName> and the <persName>Duchess of Malfi</persName>, are
                    unlike any other plays in composition and in style. There is
                    perhaps more art in the character of <persName>Vittoria</persName> than we elsewhere
                    find in <persName>Webster</persName>; the often quoted scene of her trial is the 'finest
                    instance but one of the author's dramatic power. The guilty
                    woman wears her sin so lightly that it grows an ornament; there
                    is a triumph as of innocence in her fearless bearing, her varied
                    and ready, eloquence, her facile turns of phrase, her scornful
                    argument and passionate rhetoric. It is not like innocence, but it
                    supplies the place of conviction with admiration; if we do not
                    forget her guilt, we care for it no more than she does, when her
                    calm and final words ring in our ears, making a glory out of her
                    shame, turning her condemnation to a triumph, and her judge
                    into the criminal. <persName>Brachiano</persName>, tho’ inferior to the heroine, is a
                    vigorous and careful sketch; Flamineo's colder temperament well
                    sets out the impulsive emotion of his sister’s; and in reading the last
                    scenes, we hesitate whether to award most praise to the earnest
                    eloquence of the verse or to the subtle touches of character and
                    dramatic passion.
                </p>
                <p>The <persName>Duchess of Malfi</persName>, on the whole, is the noblest specimen of
                    <persName>Webster</persName>; it is more complete and definite as a work of art, than
                    <persName>Vittoria Corombona</persName>; and its pathos is wider and "deeper. The
                    scenes before and after the murder of the Duchess are the most
                    perfect instances I know of imaginative realism. <persName>Webster</persName>would
                    have been a great poet had he never written anything but that
                    ghastly dirge, where the murderer bids a living woman perform for
                    herself the offices done for the newly dead; the sweet and holy</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">It stall not be a house of convertites;</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">My mind shall make it honester to me</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Than the Pope’s palace, and more peaceable</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Than thy soul, though thou art a Cardinal.</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-8"><persName>Vittoria Corombona</persName></l>
            </div> 
            <div type="article">
                <p>words that close as with music the dark scene of pain and evil;
                    or that dialogue between the <persName>Duke Ferdinand</persName> and his sullen, subtle
                    follower, slow to repent as to sin :—</p>
                <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2"><persName>Ferd</persName>. Cover her face: mine eyes dazzle. She died young.</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2"><persName>Bos</persName>. I think not so: her infelicity</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-3">Seemed to have years too many.</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2"><persName>Ferd</persName>. She and I were twins;</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-3">And should I die this instant, I had lived</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-3">Her time to a minute.</l>
                    <l rendition="#l-indent-2"><persName>Bos</persName>. It seems she was born first.</l>
                </quote>
                <p>There is somewhat in the man's clear, sad insight into sorrow and
                    sin, which makes one shrink. The eyes that had seen this, how did
                    they look on the common day? the ears that had taken those quiet,
                    brief words, how did they listen to the usual converse of men ?
                    One thinks of what he knew and of what he has told us, till it
                    seems as tho’ one might almost say, what had this man done, that
                    he should see such things? The prophet who beheld Pallas
                    unveiled, went away blind for ever. Is there no retribution for the
                    poet who has gone so deep into the dark places, where the sun
                    is silent.</p>
                <p>As this imperfect analysis draws to a close, its writer sees how
                    m«ch has been left unsaid—how much tacit injustice done to the
                    subject. Much more might worthily be said of either poet: and
                    will be, when the study of our noble literature is fully re-opened to
                    all. There has been enough of neglect and ignorance; it is time we
                    should know our own wealth. The earnest reverence and affectionate
                    study of a few should not be all that we can spare the mighty dead.
                    More than this must be given ; and it will be. Wise enjoyment, noble
                    and healthy teaching, lies for all in the forgotten writings of our
                    early masters. It w’as not in vain that such men thought and
                    toiled in the times we affect to praise. Too much honour cannot
                    be given to the brave clear intellect, the earnest and fearless heart
                    of such writers as these. Let us be just at length, and begin to
                    measure reputation simply by merit We who profess to love the</p>
                <list type="footnote"><item>See for a comment on this, t'he insolent and silly ‘notices* of these poets in
                    <persName>Lardner</persName>'s Eyclopaedia. The minor dramatists may take comfort, seeing that the
                    same gentleman who crushes them with judicial scorn appears, like the youthful critic
                    of <persName>Leech</persName>, to ‘ consider <persName>Shakespeare</persName> a much overrated man.</item></list>
                <p>past, and to rate it according to its desert, let us find out what it
                    was and what it has left us Because justice has not yet been done,
                    shall we perpetuate injustice ? Let us remember sometimes that we
                    have heard of</p>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">A lion that dies of an ass’s kick,</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">The wronged great soul of an ancient Master.</l>
                <p>The appeal so well and wisely made in behalf of early art,
                    I would make for our early national poets, and for no dissimilar
                    reasons, Hitherto we have merited the taunt—</p>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Here, where your praise would yield returns</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-5">And a handsome word or two give help,</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Here, after your kind, the mastiff grins,</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-5">And the puppy pack of poodles yelp.</l>
                <p>Let us hope that, considering the literary work these men did,
                    all wise students of poetry will come to heed the advice of a
                    later stanza:</p>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Give these, 1 say, full honour and glory</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-5">For daring so much, before they well did it.</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">The first of the new, in our race’s story,</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-5">Beats the last of the old, ’tis no idle quiddit.</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">The worthies began a revolution</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-5">Which if on earth we intend to acknowledge,</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-4">Honour them now (ends my allocution)</l>
                <l rendition="#l-indent-5">Nor confer our degree when the folks leave college.</l>
                <p>In this hope I close the present essay; to be followed as <choice><orig>circum-stance</orig><reg>circumstance</reg></choice> permits by others, in which the subject of our early drama
                    may be more fully treated.</p>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
