<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="oms_up.xsl"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Story of Princess Blachelys</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Generated by</resp>
                    <name>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana University</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Brianna Marshall</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Department of Information and Library Science, Indiana
                    University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date when="2013">2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>The Story of Princess Blachelys</title>
                        <author>George Birkbeck Hill</author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>Undergraduate Papers</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Oxford, England, UK</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Old Mortality Society</publisher>
                            <date when="1857-12">December 1857</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                            <!-- <biblScope type="pp"><26-30</biblScope> -->
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <p>A bright summer’s day, with a gentle breeze rustling through the green leaves
                    over head, rippling over the yellowing wheat, and coming with how pleasant a
                    whisper to him who was so happy as to be out in the fields and woods. Happy
                    indeed was that man; such a day it was that now one would go on leaping and
                    running for very joy, now walk slowly along with a calmer delight, and now lie
                    down on some mossy bank and gaze up at the white flocks of cloud that the wind
                    wove in endless variety of patterns on the deep blue ground of heaven.</p>
                <p><persName>Prince Chantefleur</persName> was too happy not to feel all the delights of that bright
                    summer day: no weather, I think, could be so bad but that a man would love it
                    the day before his marriage, and to-morrow Prince Chantefleur was to wed the
                    <persName>Princess Blanchelys</persName> of the Golden Hair. So he leapt and ran, and at times he
                    drew his sword and cleared a path through the tangle, and proud he was when he
                    laid low a tall tough thistle; for you must know that the Prince, though a head
                    taller than all his people, still was not quite five inches high.</p>
                <p>So on he went happily through the woods, full of their beauty, and dreaming of a
                    still deeper beauty. “Ah, beautiful lily” he said, as he looked up at a tall
                    flower which swung so gracefully high above his head; “you are indeed white and
                    fair, and happy is the bee that shall lie in your bosom, but I shall rest on a
                    breast still whiter, still fairer, and drink in deep of love. Yellow are the
                    graceful spears that spring up in you, from your white bosoms but golden hair
                    will float over me where 1 shall lie to-morrow/’ And the lily only smiled and
                    said “l am fair but she is fairer.” And on the happy Prince went; he talked to
                    many flowers of his lady love, and told them of her beauty, and they all said
                    "we are fair but she is fairer:" And the» mosses said “ Ah, happy Prince we have
                    often softly couched your head: our couch was soft and warm but her breast will
                    be softer and wrarmer.” But he soon forgot the fair lily and the other flowers,
                    and the soft mosses, for under a bright green fern, in glorious contrast with
                    the green, shone the golden air of his lady love.</p>
                <p>The ferns swayed over them full of delight, the gleams of sunlight broke upon
                    them, the birds sang right happily, the trees rustled gently above them, and the
                    little hare-bell rang out a merry peal of joy. And there they sat under the fern
                    leaves shade, and the sun crept on and on, and the shadow of the lily grew
                    longer and longer, and its top shone purple-white like snow, as it caught the
                    last rays of the setting day, and the breeze fell and the rustling leaves were
                    still. So the Prince and Princess rose sadly to return home, and yet not sadly,
                    for every moment brought them nearer to the glorious time when love—deep love
                    was to be theirs in all its wondrous depth. Hand in hand they went along, the
                    soft mosses became softer to their tread, the flowers bowed toward them with
                    love, the rose stole a kiss from the maiden and the lily swept the Knight's lips
                    and blushed with delight; even the rough bramble grew tender and longed sadly
                    that he were soft and gentle, that he might twine round the girl’s warm
                    neck.</p>
                <p>Right in their way rose a bed of nettles,— "Stand back dear lady and I will open
                    a path, I who fear nothing;" and the Prince drew his trusty sword and struck
                    valiantly. Ah roe, but as be smote so bravely and so deftly on this side and
                    that, he heard one cry, his name once called, and he looked round and a great
                    white bird with staring eyes was bearing off his bride. I know not what he
                    felt—he cried aloud, and then with his sword in hand, he ran wildly along trying
                    to keep up with the monster that was bearing away his life, his love, his own
                    true bride. The bushes again drew back for him, the lily rose up out of his way,
                    the moss was springy to his feet, and everything sped him on, for everything
                    that was beautiful was sick at heart. On and on he ran, crying aloud to cheer
                    his love, “ courage, dear heart, your true Knight is at hand," but all the time
                    he felt very faint, for he thought he never could save her. At last he saw the
                    great bird make for an old tower that stood up before him in the moonlight.
                    Large fir trees rose up ghost like around it, dark and gloomy; while ivy had
                    crept over three sides and had wound about the battlements at the top. It looked
                    very sad with its dark ivy and darker shadows thrown by the giant trees, that
                    whispered ghostly sounds all around them. On one side, high up, was a black
                    opening; the long ivy shoots hung all about it, half biding it and half showing
                    it, throwing shadows and lights into the recess. Hither the great bird flew with
                    his beautiful burden, just as the faithful lover rushed breathless up to the
                    foot of the tower.</p>
                <p>What could he do ? before him rose the cold brick wall, no ivy shoots within his
                    reach, for the great gnarled root crawled up the opposite side, and far above
                    his head was the black opening, and what was doing within, he dare not think
                    upon. He cried aloud that he would give up himself to save his dear bride, but
                    all the answer he heard was a scornful hooting. He tried to catch at the ivy
                    shoots, but none reached to within a full ten inches of the ground and he was
                    only half that height. Just then he heard an odd squeaking noise, that seemed to
                    come from some place close by his feet; his name was called, “ Prince, Prince, I
                    will help you : I once helped a lion out of a net. I know a way to the great
                    bird’s den: I know a secret passage up through the wall; follow me and I will
                    lead the way.” The poor prince thought he saw some chance, some hope, however
                    slight, he seized at it for what else could he do? “ The way, the way,” he
                    cried, "quick! quick!” The mouse—for it was no other—pointed to a little hole in
                    the brickwork: “ but stay” he said, "wait till I can get help, we are not strong
                    enough alone.” But never a word did the Prince answer, but taking his sword
                    between his teeth, he scrambled up and up, over rubbish that slipped beneath his
                    tread ; cutting his face and hands sadly, but never ceasing a moment, always
                    dreading he might be too late. At last he reached a level space; a sob he heard
                    in the distance was the sad guide to his steps; grasping his sword tight in his
                    hand, he rushed on. "Lady mine” he shouted out, "cheer up, I am coming, your
                    true Knight, your lover:" hs heard one cry of joy in answer and then found
                    himself fighting for his own life and for that of his beautiful bride. Well and
                    bravely did he fight, his blows fell thick and heavy. He saw deliverance before
                    him, when his foot tripped up, and in a moment the great bird had him beneath
                    her claws and was hooting in his face.</p>
                <p>But we must return to our friend the mouse. “ Ah,” saiu the mouse, who was a bit
                    of a philosopher, having come to a good old age, "that is always the way with
                    these young sparks now a days; they rush on at once, never heeding an old
                    fellow’s advice: though how runs the proverb— 'the words of an old man are like
                    the inside of a cheese.’ Ah! it was different in my younger days, we did not
                    think ourselves wiser than our elders. Well! well! it would serve him right, if
                    I were to leave him to take care of himself, but no I am a soft hearted old
                    fellow, and so must, I suppose, see what can be done. Let me see," and hereupon
                    he whisked round his tail to the tip of his nose, as all wise mice do when they
                    are engaged in deliberation. "Let me see; I have it*, I will get my cousin the
                    glow-worm to help me. For that great bird I remember hates my cousin and will
                    never come here near him, because he shines so beautifully I suppose." And
                    saying this the mouse started off to the glow-worm, who lived hard by.</p>
                <p>“ Cousin, cousin," he cried “ I want you to help me," and he told him the whole
                    story. “ Come along" said the glow-worm, "but stay you must carry me, for I
                    never was much of a walker : and look, here lie the halves of a nutshell quite
                    handy. I will jump into one and do you put the other on the top and so bear me
                    along. Now when we arrive at the hole where the bird lives, just throw down the
                    shell and I will leap out, and you will see what will happen."</p>
                <p>"All right" said the mouse, “be bold." Now to tell the truth the poor mouse said
                    this because he felt very much afraid himself and wanted to pick up a little
                    courage. At times he felt inclined to draw back, but then he thought of the poor
                    knight and the fair maiden. “ Besides" said he “ I will keep safe in the narrow
                    passage and throw my cousin into the hole, as he told me, and if he is killed
                    why I can't help it." So like a bold fellow as he was, he began the ascent; up
                    and up he climbed, never stopping to take breath, though he found the glow worm
                    and the shell a great burthen. Still as he knew the way well, and moreover was
                    famous for his climbing, he went up so quickly that he reached the top but a few
                    moments after the gallant knight had been overthrown.</p>
                <p>The great bird was still hooting fiercely and taunting the poor Prince; while the
                    beautiful princess had burst loose from her bonds and had fallen on the neck of
                    her lover; her golden hair streaming over his face and her tears wetting his
                    cheeks. They were never to meet any more they thought, and yet dying together it
                    was not so very bitter.</p>
                <p>But just then a slight noise was heard; something dropped on the floor, out
                    rolled a ball of light, shining straight into the eyes of the great bird; never
                    I ween had the glow-worm sent forth so bright a ray. The bird was blinded by the
                    light—for of all animals that lived he loved the darkness most—and stumbled
                    backwards, losing his hold on the knight, “ Lose me, dearest" said the prince,
                    and her soft arms fell from his neck ; he leapt to his feet and in an instant
                    buried his sword deep into the monster’s breast. His love, his bride was safe,
                    and to-morrow was their marriage day. He took her in his arms and kissed her
                    again and again, and they both wept for joy and gladness, and then they kissed
                    away each other's tears. I trow there were many kisses needed.</p>
                <p>Then they thanked the bright glow-worm and the good old mouse; and the glow-worm
                    made a polite speech, and said his own poor light was extinguished by the lady's
                    bright eyes, and the silly old mouse put his head out of the hole, to see as he
                    pretended if it were a starlight night, but in reality to hide a tear. At last,
                    however, they set out for home, the mouse claiming to be their guide and the
                    glow-worm their torch. The moon shone brightly, and the flowers were all happy
                    again, and the nightingale sang in deep joy, and the knight’s arm wound round
                    his lady-love's waist, for he feared he might lose her once more. Great was the
                    joy when they reached the court and told their story, the two old kings, the
                    fathers of the bride and bridegroom, could hardly say a word, but fell on their
                    children's necks and kissed them again and again ; and as for the courtiers, why
                    some were laughing and some were weeping, in such a manner that you would have
                    hardly known if it were a funeral or a wedding. Who can tell all the festivities
                    that followed? Never had such a sight been seen; never was any marriage
                    celebrated more royally ; never was any bride so fair, never any knight so
                    brave. Of course the mouse and the glow-worm were both present; the former for
                    his great services was decorated with the Grand Cross of the Toasted Cheese, the
                    latter was made First Candlestick in Waiting, and in this capacity he had the
                    glory of lighting the noble pair as they went in deep joy from the great old
                    hall to their happy bridal chamber.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
